<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>zhaiyuSCI</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.zhaiyusci.net/</id><updated>2018-01-07T16:10:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>ydvr: A C++ implement of DVR method</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/ydvr-a-c-implement-of-dvr-method.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-07T16:10:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-01-07T16:10:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2018-01-07:/ydvr-a-c-implement-of-dvr-method.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudo-spectral_method"&gt;DVR&lt;/a&gt; method is an important method to deal with the nuclear motion problem.  In the old days, Fortran is used to write almost all the scientific computation codes.  However, Fortran is dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, people has been able to code in more powerful and popular language like Python and Matlab.  That's …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudo-spectral_method"&gt;DVR&lt;/a&gt; method is an important method to deal with the nuclear motion problem.  In the old days, Fortran is used to write almost all the scientific computation codes.  However, Fortran is dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, people has been able to code in more powerful and popular language like Python and Matlab.  That's good.  But personally I do not like Matlab because it is not a open standard and python because of the indent syntax and the difference between py2 and py3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C++, however, is an 'old' language but still very important these days.  I mean, you can still find a lot of scientific libraries in C++ and because it is one of the most important systematical language it cannot die in the near future.  C++ is object-oriented so it is easier to be reused by other guys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when I had the will to rebuild a DVR code I think C++ is a good choice.  Besides, I came up a 'new' trick for PODVR (actually not new: it is directly from the &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/000926149285330D"&gt;original paper&lt;/a&gt; of PODVR).  The H0 operator can actually including all the 1D Hamiltonian so that we can make the potential energy matrix the most correct, if you know the fact that in DVR, the errors are directly from the potential part because the localized basis function for a DVR point/grid are only 'quasi-localized'.  So it is necessary to rebuild the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find my codes &lt;a href="https://github.com/zhaiyusci/ydvr"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Quantum Harmonic Oscillator as a training material for young theoretical chemists</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/quantum-harmonic-oscillator-as-a-training-material-for-young-theoretical-chemists.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-27T22:30:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-06-27T22:30:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2017-06-27:/quantum-harmonic-oscillator-as-a-training-material-for-young-theoretical-chemists.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I know, a lot of famous universities in North America and Europe train their young scientist with pretty hard jobs.  It is not always the same situation here in China, oh, mainland of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In China, the courses are often limited to 'introduction'.  Most of the professors introduce the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I know, a lot of famous universities in North America and Europe train their young scientist with pretty hard jobs.  It is not always the same situation here in China, oh, mainland of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In China, the courses are often limited to 'introduction'.  Most of the professors introduce the basic ideas of the subject, and the students finish the exercises in the textbook, which is aims at the graduate school entrance examination.   However, in the famous universities, the homework can be very difficult to solve, and often need the students to finish some reading tasks and some programming.  The place where I got the idea is OCW of many universities like MIT.  A good example is list &lt;a href="http://www.scs.illinois.edu/~sohirata/education.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;(Professor So Hirata's page).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am now a Ph. D. candidate and I need help my professor train young graduate students.  Actually, in the future, when I have my own team (although perhaps I could spoil that...), I need train my own students.  What should I do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my plan.  As I am working on Theoretical Chemistry in the 21st century, my students need to know how to program.  So I look into the textbook of spectroscopy, in which field I am making efforts, to find the good examples for the primers.  Quantum Harmonic Oscillator is a good example to train programming for several reasons. (a) You do not need a eigensolver, which is always hard for guys of chemistry major, to know its eigenvalue and eigenfunction (of course we are talking about Hamiltonian here); (b) The eigenfunction is analytically available . However, to get the function, a subroutine to calculate the Hermite polynomials, which a sets of unlimited number orthogonal functions with recursion relation; (c) To finish the job, all the important syntaxes in FORTRAN are used.  Yes, we still use FORTRAN. But I think it is not a big deal if you want to use another language.  As I am informed, python is one of the most popular programming languages in science education.  One more thing is that the finished subroutines, the eigenfunctions of harmonic oscillator, can be used as the basis set to solve 1D quantum oscillator, although the main method we use in &lt;a href="http://huiligroup.org/"&gt;Li group&lt;/a&gt; is sinc DVR. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The job I gave the younger students is composing a program to draw the picture like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_harmonic_oscillator#/media/File:HarmOsziFunktionen.png"&gt;the one on Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ask my young lab mates to finish the job by Friday.  I will give an example here after that here on my blog.  Notice that the visualization codes are not needed. They just need to work out the input file of some plot tools.  I do not want to make the job too hard.  I also tell them that maybe they can just work out the first five functions instead of the general one (again, less hard problem, but it is for primers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish them good luck.  I will post my program here, although it will not be the best solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sevaral days later...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The codes is available &lt;a href="https://github.com/zhaiyusci/theor.chem.primers"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>No more GOTO!</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/no-more-goto.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-28T22:30:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-10-28T22:30:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-10-28:/no-more-goto.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you are working on scientific calculation, you must know FORTRAN.  Hence you will meet a lot of &lt;code&gt;GOTO&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I JUST HATE IT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;GOTO&lt;/code&gt; looks like interchange.  Well, it is good for crossroad.  But frankly speaking, I do not know how to drive :-(.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read blogs saying that, if you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you are working on scientific calculation, you must know FORTRAN.  Hence you will meet a lot of &lt;code&gt;GOTO&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I JUST HATE IT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;GOTO&lt;/code&gt; looks like interchange.  Well, it is good for crossroad.  But frankly speaking, I do not know how to drive :-(.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read blogs saying that, if you are a new guy in a group, &lt;strong&gt;DO NOT REFACTORING THE OLD UGLY FORTRAN CODES&lt;/strong&gt;.  Although I am not new here, I prefer let the code be &lt;em&gt;as it was&lt;/em&gt;.  However, some guys should know that FORTRAN is not popular any more in certain situations and I think it time that we should try to use more elegant languages, like the new C++(well, too complicated) or python(but I dislike it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is &lt;a href="http://fortranwiki.org/fortran/show/Modernizing+Old+Fortran"&gt;a webpage&lt;/a&gt; which told us how to do 'modernization' to your old FORTRAN code.  I will read it carefully and try it.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Limit memory usage of a single process</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/limit-memory-usage-of-a-single-process.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-08T22:30:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-10-08T22:30:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-10-08:/limit-memory-usage-of-a-single-process.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you are a computational scientist, I mean, not matter what you are working on, deep learning, computational physics, computational chemistry, etc., and if you use C++.  It is likely that you write a program to leak the momery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a disaster!!!  Anyone run Linux on his/her own …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you are a computational scientist, I mean, not matter what you are working on, deep learning, computational physics, computational chemistry, etc., and if you use C++.  It is likely that you write a program to leak the momery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a disaster!!!  Anyone run Linux on his/her own laptop and write a code like this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;){&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;double&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(I know the readers are not idiots and will not write program like this.) will find that your computer just dead in like a minute.  But frankly speaking, if you build a class and it has a construction function without a proper distruction function, and maybe one of the members of the class is a pointer, memory leaking happens, and this is a common mistake, even if you are a smart guy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also know that if you are a computational scientist you may not want to check if there is enough momery to "new" something, just because it is waste of time and come on, we are not professional programmer!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, when we debug a program in our laptop, what should we do?  A good choice is to put your program in a box.  If the memory inside the box runs out, just kill the program withour kill the mechine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a Chinese.  So I search online in Chinese.  Unfortunately, there is not single one solution for this in Chinese world.  Luckily, there is one solution, which is exactly what we want. &lt;a href="https://github.com/pshved/timeout"&gt;Timeout&lt;/a&gt; is a script that limit the memory and time use of a process.  To use it, it is simple&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;timeout -m &lt;span class="m"&gt;1000000&lt;/span&gt; ./qmc.x -d &lt;span class="m"&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here, the '-m 1000000' is to set the maxium memory of the following command &lt;code&gt;./qmc.x -d 1000&lt;/code&gt;, and the unit of the memory is KiB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it is not the manual of it. Just go the the github page for more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, thanks to the author of the script, &lt;a href="http://coldattic.info/shvedsky/pro/blogs/a-foo-walks-into-a-bar"&gt;Pavel Shved&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>MANPATH ${MANPATH} $(manpath)</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/manpath-manpath-manpath.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-30T20:30:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-08-30T20:30:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-08-30:/manpath-manpath-manpath.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the past, I only set the shell variable &lt;code&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt; to make the software compiledby me can be found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And after I installed TeXLive 2016 I learnt how to set &lt;code&gt;MANPATH&lt;/code&gt;, which allows me to use man to browse the manual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But today, I find what I was doing is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the past, I only set the shell variable &lt;code&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt; to make the software compiledby me can be found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And after I installed TeXLive 2016 I learnt how to set &lt;code&gt;MANPATH&lt;/code&gt;, which allows me to use man to browse the manual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But today, I find what I was doing is absolutely wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use Linux Mint 18.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the way I set &lt;code&gt;MANPATH&lt;/code&gt; was like this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;MANPATH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/path/to/the/man/page:&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;MANPATH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, that is wrong because in this way, the &lt;code&gt;MANPATH&lt;/code&gt; variable is set and the &lt;code&gt;mandb&lt;/code&gt; no longer scans the system file &lt;code&gt;/etc/manpath.config&lt;/code&gt;, which is relied by all the, how to say, native program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If &lt;code&gt;mandb&lt;/code&gt; runs, it will give a line like this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;mandb&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;warning&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;$MANPATH&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kd"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ignoring&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sr"&gt;/etc/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;manpath&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The reason is that, in Ubuntu based system, as I read online, the MANPATH is null by default.  Yes, the system will create the database and yes, the &lt;code&gt;man&lt;/code&gt; works for all the program like &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; and all the program installed via &lt;code&gt;apt&lt;/code&gt;.  But the system &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; set the variable &lt;code&gt;MANPATH&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right way to set it is like this, as far as I tested&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;unset&lt;/span&gt; MANPATH
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;MANPATH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;manpath -q&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# somthing else&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;MANPATH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/path/to/the/man/page:&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;MANPATH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# something else&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The second line up there is to set the MANPATH the initial value it should be as the &lt;code&gt;/etc/manpath.config&lt;/code&gt; is sourced.  &lt;em&gt;Notice that the first line is also indispensible 'cause the &lt;code&gt;manpath&lt;/code&gt; excutable will ignore &lt;code&gt;/etc/manpath.config&lt;/code&gt; as well if &lt;code&gt;MANPATH&lt;/code&gt; is set&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Diffusion Monte Carlo Methods and Trial Function</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/diffusion-monte-carlo-methods-and-trial-function.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-21T14:40:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-08-21T14:40:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-08-21:/diffusion-monte-carlo-methods-and-trial-function.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For complex quantum system, the variation method is no longer useful for tho solve the problem precisely, you need a basis set of quite a large size.  &lt;em&gt;Quantum simulation&lt;/em&gt; is used in such system.  &lt;em&gt;Monte Carlo Method&lt;/em&gt; is widely used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I began to learn about these methods.  Notice that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For complex quantum system, the variation method is no longer useful for tho solve the problem precisely, you need a basis set of quite a large size.  &lt;em&gt;Quantum simulation&lt;/em&gt; is used in such system.  &lt;em&gt;Monte Carlo Method&lt;/em&gt; is widely used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I began to learn about these methods.  Notice that I say 'these' because methods can be called 'Quantum Monte Carlo' are more than three ones. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diffusion Monte Carlo is a, well, good idea.  I recommend &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/RevModPhys.73.33"&gt;Rev. Mod. Phys. 73, 33 (2001)&lt;/a&gt; as a reference.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that if you use &lt;em&gt;mixed estimator&lt;/em&gt; to get the energy, something terrible happened.   Just assume that the trial function is the eigenfunction of the ground state, which means actually we have got the right answer.  No matter whether your simulation converges to the walkers' distribution or not, the energy mixed estimator will give the answer -- the eigenvalue of ground state.  Similarly, if the trial function is the eigenfunction of the first excited state, the estimator will give the answer of first excited state, the reason is that the 'local energy' is relate to the trial function.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let us simply do the superposition, to get the wave function for the superposition state of ground state and first excited state (just ignore the re-normalization).  Of course, the simulation answer shall be a value between the ground state energy and first excited state energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have coded the Diffusion Monte Carlo method and test it on the harmonic oscillator system.  It is true: the mixed estimator is highly dependent on the trial function.  Watch out!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>How to use GaussView5 via ssh</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/how-to-use-gaussview5-via-ssh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-05-26T22:30:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-05-26T22:30:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-05-26:/how-to-use-gaussview5-via-ssh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it seems that a lot of people (including the past me) do not know how to use GaussView in a server.  Say, it is fairly difficult to set the X server up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://huiligroup.org/"&gt;Prof. Li&lt;/a&gt; and I want to use it.  Actually, Prof. Li was going to let me help …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it seems that a lot of people (including the past me) do not know how to use GaussView in a server.  Say, it is fairly difficult to set the X server up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://huiligroup.org/"&gt;Prof. Li&lt;/a&gt; and I want to use it.  Actually, Prof. Li was going to let me help him install a copy on his Macbook.  However, we find that we do not have the copyright to do so.  But our institute do buy the software, at least for the server.  But we found it did not work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason is that in the past IT engineer from ITC set the environment variable &lt;code&gt;DISPLAY&lt;/code&gt; as a value (Why? I do not know).  And there do be some essay online told us that you should set things up in your &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; like this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;REMOTEHOST&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sb"&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;who am i &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; sed -n &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;s/.*(\([^) ]*\).*/\1/p; 1q&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sb"&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;DISPLAY&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;REMOTEHOST&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;:0
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Er, it is not that right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prof. Li told me that when he worked in uwaterloo, it is easy.  You can just type &lt;code&gt;ssh -Y xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx&lt;/code&gt; to login and &lt;code&gt;gv&lt;/code&gt;.  Well...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back from Prof. Li's office, I find that what I am using, &lt;a href="http://mobaxterm.mobatek.net/"&gt;MobaXterm&lt;/a&gt;, can easily open its X server automatically.  It came to me that maybe there is something MobaXterm do but we do not know.  I check its setting and find it enable the X forwarding and I read the man page of ssh, it is what &lt;code&gt;-Y&lt;/code&gt; do.  And what is more, MobaXterm can setup &lt;code&gt;DISPLAY&lt;/code&gt; automatically.  So, maybe &lt;code&gt;ssh -Y&lt;/code&gt; can do the same thing.  But there is some different.  I think &lt;code&gt;ssh -Y&lt;/code&gt; will not change &lt;code&gt;DISPLAY&lt;/code&gt; if it has been set, like this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; x&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$DISPLAY&lt;/span&gt; -ne x &lt;span class="o"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;then&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;DISPLAY&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;xxx &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# I do not know what it actually does,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I comment out the line in &lt;code&gt;~/.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; problem solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also true if you are using Molden from server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And again, I recommend MobaXterm to you.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Interesting details about vdW system</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/interesting-details-about-vdw-system.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-04-09T22:20:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-04-09T22:20:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-04-09:/interesting-details-about-vdw-system.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/damping-function-in-morselong-range-potential-energy-model.html"&gt;a previous blog&lt;/a&gt;, I introduced some tiny little progressing in build a PES.  But a mistake was made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I coded, I forget to share the common variable of bdamp.  SO, IT IS PROVED AT LEAST IN THE SYSTEM I BUILT(OCS-H2) AN ANGULAR FUNCTION IS NOT NEEDED FOR …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/damping-function-in-morselong-range-potential-energy-model.html"&gt;a previous blog&lt;/a&gt;, I introduced some tiny little progressing in build a PES.  But a mistake was made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I coded, I forget to share the common variable of bdamp.  SO, IT IS PROVED AT LEAST IN THE SYSTEM I BUILT(OCS-H2) AN ANGULAR FUNCTION IS NOT NEEDED FOR BDAMP. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the truth is the fitting error is decreasing. So, the right damping function for MLR is of vital importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we find that the new PES is better, but not better enough to represent the experiments. What is wrong?  I will talk about it in this year's ISMS.  A work which concerns about the inter- intra- molecular vibration coupling has been done.  Now I need more data to validate my theory.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Damping function in Morse/Long-Range Potential Energy Model</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/damping-function-in-morselong-range-potential-energy-model.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-03-12T22:20:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-03-12T22:20:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-03-12:/damping-function-in-morselong-range-potential-energy-model.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is a great success that the application of Morse/Long-Range (MLR) in van der Waals (vdW) complex.  MLR is devloped by R. J. Le Roy et al..  You may want to use it when building you own bi-atomic system model.  That's cool and you can always use &lt;a href="http://scienide2.uwaterloo.ca/~rleroy/betaFIT/"&gt;betaFIT&lt;/a&gt;, where …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is a great success that the application of Morse/Long-Range (MLR) in van der Waals (vdW) complex.  MLR is devloped by R. J. Le Roy et al..  You may want to use it when building you own bi-atomic system model.  That's cool and you can always use &lt;a href="http://scienide2.uwaterloo.ca/~rleroy/betaFIT/"&gt;betaFIT&lt;/a&gt;, where you can get the code and manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, MLR had difficulty in &lt;em&gt;short range&lt;/em&gt; (as its name, it focused on &lt;em&gt;long range&lt;/em&gt;).  It means that you can use a inverse power model to represent the long range behaviour of a system, like when the two monomers in the complex distants away by 10 Angstrom or more.  But in long range, the coefficients of the inverse power terms tend to be 0 for the electrons there merge together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, Prof Le Roy came up with the damping function (Yeppy!) which can fit this decrease when the nuclear distance vanishes.  If you wanna get the details, please read &lt;a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00268976.2010.527304#.VuQoRSbAPtQ"&gt;Mol. Phys., 109, 435 (2011)&lt;/a&gt;.  By the way, this modified damping function has already been included in the newest version of betaFIT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acctually today, I enhanced the MLR in Multi Dimension system by adding a Modified Tang-Tonnies damping function with the paramenter in it as a function of angles.  By this way, I have managed the fitting error one the third of the previous model.  I will going to talk about this topic in this years ISMS in UIUC.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Neuron-Network Pontential Energy Surfaces</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/neuron-network-pontential-energy-surfaces.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-14T23:10:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-02-14T23:10:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-02-14:/neuron-network-pontential-energy-surfaces.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year I read something about Neuron-Network Potential Energy Surface (NNPES) and I think it is worth learning.
Here are my notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One recommended paper one should read is &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/c1cp21668f"&gt;PCCP, 13, 17930 (2011)&lt;/a&gt; by Joerg Behler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I do not want to introduce the detail of the idea, because paper …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year I read something about Neuron-Network Potential Energy Surface (NNPES) and I think it is worth learning.
Here are my notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One recommended paper one should read is &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/c1cp21668f"&gt;PCCP, 13, 17930 (2011)&lt;/a&gt; by Joerg Behler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I do not want to introduce the detail of the idea, because paper above give a nice definition.  NNPES do be a clever ider for it ignore the difficult physics in the problem.  Instead, it use a pure mathematical way to fit the pointwise energies (here we call it 'training').&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some guys argue that this methods just give a NNPES without a deeply conprehension of the model.  That is true.  However, this method give an effective way to let scientific guys to run MD or MC.  Somehow it is like &lt;em&gt;ab initio&lt;/em&gt; way if one take the electronic methods as black box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be kept in mind that in all NNPES is not that suitable for the high accuracy.  One can read &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.4904546"&gt;Dong H Zhang and his co-workers' work&lt;/a&gt; to see how they got an accurate result with the help of spline.  I once tried one PES fitting using NN of the system of tri-boron (thanks to D.-Z. Yang), you can find that the NN works, but does not work accurately.  &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>