<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>zhaiyuSCI - Science</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/feeds/science.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.zhaiyusci.net/</id><updated>2018-01-07T16:10:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>ydvr: A C++ implement of DVR method</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/ydvr-a-c-implement-of-dvr-method.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-07T16:10:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-01-07T16:10:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2018-01-07:/ydvr-a-c-implement-of-dvr-method.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudo-spectral_method"&gt;DVR&lt;/a&gt; method is an important method to deal with the nuclear motion problem.  In the old days, Fortran is used to write almost all the scientific computation codes.  However, Fortran is dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, people has been able to code in more powerful and popular language like Python and Matlab.  That's …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pseudo-spectral_method"&gt;DVR&lt;/a&gt; method is an important method to deal with the nuclear motion problem.  In the old days, Fortran is used to write almost all the scientific computation codes.  However, Fortran is dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, people has been able to code in more powerful and popular language like Python and Matlab.  That's good.  But personally I do not like Matlab because it is not a open standard and python because of the indent syntax and the difference between py2 and py3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C++, however, is an 'old' language but still very important these days.  I mean, you can still find a lot of scientific libraries in C++ and because it is one of the most important systematical language it cannot die in the near future.  C++ is object-oriented so it is easier to be reused by other guys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when I had the will to rebuild a DVR code I think C++ is a good choice.  Besides, I came up a 'new' trick for PODVR (actually not new: it is directly from the &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/000926149285330D"&gt;original paper&lt;/a&gt; of PODVR).  The H0 operator can actually including all the 1D Hamiltonian so that we can make the potential energy matrix the most correct, if you know the fact that in DVR, the errors are directly from the potential part because the localized basis function for a DVR point/grid are only 'quasi-localized'.  So it is necessary to rebuild the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find my codes &lt;a href="https://github.com/zhaiyusci/ydvr"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Diffusion Monte Carlo Methods and Trial Function</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/diffusion-monte-carlo-methods-and-trial-function.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-21T14:40:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-08-21T14:40:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-08-21:/diffusion-monte-carlo-methods-and-trial-function.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For complex quantum system, the variation method is no longer useful for tho solve the problem precisely, you need a basis set of quite a large size.  &lt;em&gt;Quantum simulation&lt;/em&gt; is used in such system.  &lt;em&gt;Monte Carlo Method&lt;/em&gt; is widely used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I began to learn about these methods.  Notice that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For complex quantum system, the variation method is no longer useful for tho solve the problem precisely, you need a basis set of quite a large size.  &lt;em&gt;Quantum simulation&lt;/em&gt; is used in such system.  &lt;em&gt;Monte Carlo Method&lt;/em&gt; is widely used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I began to learn about these methods.  Notice that I say 'these' because methods can be called 'Quantum Monte Carlo' are more than three ones. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diffusion Monte Carlo is a, well, good idea.  I recommend &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1103/RevModPhys.73.33"&gt;Rev. Mod. Phys. 73, 33 (2001)&lt;/a&gt; as a reference.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that if you use &lt;em&gt;mixed estimator&lt;/em&gt; to get the energy, something terrible happened.   Just assume that the trial function is the eigenfunction of the ground state, which means actually we have got the right answer.  No matter whether your simulation converges to the walkers' distribution or not, the energy mixed estimator will give the answer -- the eigenvalue of ground state.  Similarly, if the trial function is the eigenfunction of the first excited state, the estimator will give the answer of first excited state, the reason is that the 'local energy' is relate to the trial function.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let us simply do the superposition, to get the wave function for the superposition state of ground state and first excited state (just ignore the re-normalization).  Of course, the simulation answer shall be a value between the ground state energy and first excited state energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have coded the Diffusion Monte Carlo method and test it on the harmonic oscillator system.  It is true: the mixed estimator is highly dependent on the trial function.  Watch out!&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Interesting details about vdW system</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/interesting-details-about-vdw-system.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-04-09T22:20:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-04-09T22:20:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-04-09:/interesting-details-about-vdw-system.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/damping-function-in-morselong-range-potential-energy-model.html"&gt;a previous blog&lt;/a&gt;, I introduced some tiny little progressing in build a PES.  But a mistake was made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I coded, I forget to share the common variable of bdamp.  SO, IT IS PROVED AT LEAST IN THE SYSTEM I BUILT(OCS-H2) AN ANGULAR FUNCTION IS NOT NEEDED FOR …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/damping-function-in-morselong-range-potential-energy-model.html"&gt;a previous blog&lt;/a&gt;, I introduced some tiny little progressing in build a PES.  But a mistake was made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I coded, I forget to share the common variable of bdamp.  SO, IT IS PROVED AT LEAST IN THE SYSTEM I BUILT(OCS-H2) AN ANGULAR FUNCTION IS NOT NEEDED FOR BDAMP. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the truth is the fitting error is decreasing. So, the right damping function for MLR is of vital importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we find that the new PES is better, but not better enough to represent the experiments. What is wrong?  I will talk about it in this year's ISMS.  A work which concerns about the inter- intra- molecular vibration coupling has been done.  Now I need more data to validate my theory.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Damping function in Morse/Long-Range Potential Energy Model</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/damping-function-in-morselong-range-potential-energy-model.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-03-12T22:20:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-03-12T22:20:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-03-12:/damping-function-in-morselong-range-potential-energy-model.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is a great success that the application of Morse/Long-Range (MLR) in van der Waals (vdW) complex.  MLR is devloped by R. J. Le Roy et al..  You may want to use it when building you own bi-atomic system model.  That's cool and you can always use &lt;a href="http://scienide2.uwaterloo.ca/~rleroy/betaFIT/"&gt;betaFIT&lt;/a&gt;, where …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It is a great success that the application of Morse/Long-Range (MLR) in van der Waals (vdW) complex.  MLR is devloped by R. J. Le Roy et al..  You may want to use it when building you own bi-atomic system model.  That's cool and you can always use &lt;a href="http://scienide2.uwaterloo.ca/~rleroy/betaFIT/"&gt;betaFIT&lt;/a&gt;, where you can get the code and manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, MLR had difficulty in &lt;em&gt;short range&lt;/em&gt; (as its name, it focused on &lt;em&gt;long range&lt;/em&gt;).  It means that you can use a inverse power model to represent the long range behaviour of a system, like when the two monomers in the complex distants away by 10 Angstrom or more.  But in long range, the coefficients of the inverse power terms tend to be 0 for the electrons there merge together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, Prof Le Roy came up with the damping function (Yeppy!) which can fit this decrease when the nuclear distance vanishes.  If you wanna get the details, please read &lt;a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00268976.2010.527304#.VuQoRSbAPtQ"&gt;Mol. Phys., 109, 435 (2011)&lt;/a&gt;.  By the way, this modified damping function has already been included in the newest version of betaFIT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acctually today, I enhanced the MLR in Multi Dimension system by adding a Modified Tang-Tonnies damping function with the paramenter in it as a function of angles.  By this way, I have managed the fitting error one the third of the previous model.  I will going to talk about this topic in this years ISMS in UIUC.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Neuron-Network Pontential Energy Surfaces</title><link href="http://www.zhaiyusci.net/neuron-network-pontential-energy-surfaces.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-14T23:10:00+08:00</published><updated>2016-02-14T23:10:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Yu Zhai</name></author><id>tag:www.zhaiyusci.net,2016-02-14:/neuron-network-pontential-energy-surfaces.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year I read something about Neuron-Network Potential Energy Surface (NNPES) and I think it is worth learning.
Here are my notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One recommended paper one should read is &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/c1cp21668f"&gt;PCCP, 13, 17930 (2011)&lt;/a&gt; by Joerg Behler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I do not want to introduce the detail of the idea, because paper …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year I read something about Neuron-Network Potential Energy Surface (NNPES) and I think it is worth learning.
Here are my notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One recommended paper one should read is &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1039/c1cp21668f"&gt;PCCP, 13, 17930 (2011)&lt;/a&gt; by Joerg Behler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I do not want to introduce the detail of the idea, because paper above give a nice definition.  NNPES do be a clever ider for it ignore the difficult physics in the problem.  Instead, it use a pure mathematical way to fit the pointwise energies (here we call it 'training').&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some guys argue that this methods just give a NNPES without a deeply conprehension of the model.  That is true.  However, this method give an effective way to let scientific guys to run MD or MC.  Somehow it is like &lt;em&gt;ab initio&lt;/em&gt; way if one take the electronic methods as black box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be kept in mind that in all NNPES is not that suitable for the high accuracy.  One can read &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.4904546"&gt;Dong H Zhang and his co-workers' work&lt;/a&gt; to see how they got an accurate result with the help of spline.  I once tried one PES fitting using NN of the system of tri-boron (thanks to D.-Z. Yang), you can find that the NN works, but does not work accurately.  &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>